{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Mitterrand Doctrine provided amnesty for members of this group who had renounced violence. This group carried out its most famous action to oppose attempts at a “historic compromise”. This group’s deadliest act was the bombing of the Central Train Station in Bologna. Mario Moretti led this group, which primarily operated during the Years of Lead. For ten points, name this group of Italian communists who kidnapped and murdered Prime Minister Aldo Moro in 1978.",
      "answer": "Red Brigades or Brigate Rosse"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire was ruled under the Kouroukan Fouga constitution, which established the Gbara legislature. A victory at the Battle of Kirina solidified this empire’s rule over the Sosso leader Sumanguru. Chihab al-Umari documented the travels of one ruler of this empire, who supposedly built a mosque every Friday on his hajj to Mecca. For ten points, name this West African empire that was founded by Sundiata Keita and led in the 14th century by Mansa Musa.",
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This successor of John Smith was investigated after his party accepted loans in exchange for peerage appointments in the Cash for Honours scandal. This proponent of a “Third way” between capitalism and socialism mediated the Good Friday Agreement, which ended the Troubles in Northern Ireland. This Prime Minister backed George W. Bush’s invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq. For ten points, name this “New Labour” Prime Minister of Great Britain from 1997 to 2007.",
      "answer": "Tony Blair"
    },
    {
      "question": "This speaker noted “I want [slavery] root and branch destroyed” in an 1867 speech to the American Equal Rights Association that ended with a singing of “We are going home.” This speaker asked “Where did your Christ come from?”, noting “Man had nothing to do with Him!” in another speech; in that speech, she proclaimed “I have plowed and planted, [...] and no man could head me!” for ten points, name this 19th century activist and orator, a former slave who repeated the question “Ain’t I a Woman?” in her most famous speech.",
      "answer": "Sojourner Truth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prokhorovka Cathedral commemorates the victory in this battle, which was followed by the Third Battle of Kharkov. The Allied invasion of Sicily led Heinz Guderian to argue that Nazi forces should be held back as a reserve during this battle. This battle, also known as Operation Citadel, saw the introduction of the Panzer tank as a counter to Soviet T-34s. For ten points, name this most destructive aerial battle and largest tank battle in history, fought in 1943 near a namesake Soviet town.",
      "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to costs, Canadian Prime Minister John Diefenbaker scrapped one of these technologies, the Avro Arrow. One example of this technology, which crashed in a Paris exhibition in 1973, was the Tupolev Tu-144; the only other commercial use of this type of vehicle ended after a 2000 disaster, also in Paris. The Bell X-1, piloted by Chuck Yaeger, was the first example of, for ten points, what type of aircraft that can surpass Mach 1?",
      "answer": [
        "supersonic aircraft",
        "descriptions of an airplane that can break the speed of sound, including break Mach 1 before it’s mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Abraham Lincoln responded to one of this man’s letters by explaining “If I could save the Union without freeing any slave, I would do it,” a few weeks before issuing the Emancipation Proclamation. This author of the “Prayer of Twenty Millions” died a few weeks after he lost a Presidential election, so his 66 electoral votes were split to other candidates. The phrase “Go west, young man!” was popularized by, for ten points, what editor of the New York Tribune, who lost to Ulysses Grant in the 1872 Presidential election?",
      "answer": "Horace Greeley"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist depicted one of his subjects wearing the Collar of Esses livery chain. A much-copied, though lost, work by this artist depicts his royal patron holding a glove in one hand and reaching for a dagger in the other. He included a polyhedral sundial and a lute with a broken string in a double portrait best known for a memento mori rendered in anamorphic perspective. For ten points, what portraitist of Sir Thomas More and Henry VIII included a distorted skull in The Ambassadors?",
      "answer": "Hans Holbein the Younger"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader had a nuclear bunker built in the town of Gbadolite. This leader was personally protected by the Special Presidential Division, and changed his name to refer to him going “from conquest to conquest, leaving fire in his wake” in the “Authenticity” campaign. This ruler came to power at the end of a civil war sparked by the secession of the Katanga region, but Laurent Desire-Kabila overthrew him during the First Congo War. For ten points, name this former dictator of Zaire.",
      "answer": "Mobutu Sese Seko"
    },
    {
      "question": "Darwin Judge and Charles McMahon were killed in a rocket strike on this city’s airport. Irving Berlin’s “White Christmas” was used to signal Operation Frequent Wind, which evacuated this city via airlift. Helicopters were ditched into the sea to provide more room on aircraft carriers for refugees from this city, whose Tan Son Nhut airport was bombed starting on April 29th, 1975. For ten points, name this South Vietnamese capital city, now named for Ho Chi Minh, whose fall marked the end of the Vietnam War.",
      "answer": "Saigon"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler ceded territory to Safavid Persia in the Treaty of Resht and the Treaty of Ganja. This ruler’s reform of the church was implemented by Theophan Prokopovich. During the early years of his reign, this ruler reigned alongside his brother, Ivan V. This ruler won territory from Charles XII after signing the Treaty of Nystad at the end of the Great Northern War. The Battle of Poltava was won by forces under, for ten points, what westernizing Russian tsar who built a city once known as Leningrad?",
        "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter undertook a Grand Embassy to the west, but returned prematurely to brutally address this 1698 uprising of these Russian armed guards.",
        "answer": "Streltsy Uprising or Revolt, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While playing against one team from this city in 2012, Joey Barton earned a 12-game suspension for attacking Carlos Tevez, Vincent Kompany, and Sergio Aguero. In that game, Aguero’s 94th minute goal for a team from this city defeated Queens Park Rangers to clinch a title at the expense of another team from this city. That team from this city has suffered under managers David Moyes and Louis van Gaal since the 2013 retirement of Sir Alex Ferguson. For ten points, name this English city whose rival clubs, City and United, have won fifteen of the 23 Premier League titles.",
        "answer": "Manchester"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The only teams to win an English Premier League title are the two Manchester clubs, Arsenal, Blackburn Rovers, and this club, which defended its 2015 title by falling as far as 16th in the table.",
        "answer": "Chelsea F.C."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Zetra Olympic Hall, a former ice rink, was reduced to rubble and civilians were bombed twice at the Markale open-air market. During this war, the Scorpions paramilitary force assisted troops under Ratko Mladi’c [m’lah-ditch] in killing over 8,000 Muslims in the Srebrenica [s’reh-breh-NEET-zah] Massacre. NATO forces eventually brought this war to a 1995 ceasefire. For ten points, name this war, which began with Slobodan Milosevic’s Serbian forces laying siege to Sarajevo.",
        "answer": "Bosnian War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The agreement ending the Bosnian War was signed in Paris after being negotiated at this western Ohio city’s Wright-Patterson Air Force Base.",
        "answer": "Dayton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event prevented a plebiscite proposed by Kurt Schuschnigg [shush-nig]. The Mauthausen-Gusen campwasestablishedshortlyafterthisevent, whichwasdeclarednullandvoidbytheMoscowDeclaration. This event was encouraged by Arthur Seyss-Inquart, and led to the resignation of President Wilhelm Miklas. This event established the province of Ostmark under the justification of lebensraum, and was followed by the annexation of the Sudetenland. For ten points, name this 1938 event in which Nazi Germany annexed Austria.",
        "answer": [
          "Anschluss",
          "Nazi annexation of Austria before 1938 is mentioned, prompting on partial answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A political union between Austria and Germany was explicitly forbidden by the Treaty of Versailles, signed by Germany, and this treaty, signed by German-Austria at the end of World War I.",
        "answer": "Treaty of St. Germain-en-Laye"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire faced the Alid revolt of Mohammed the Pure Soul, and a century later, the slaves of Basra rose up against this empire in the Zanj rebellion. One ruler of this dynasty sent a chess set and water clock to Charlemagne and built a House of Wisdom that was destroyed in Hulagu Khan’s 1258 siege of its capital, Baghdad. Avicenna and al-Khwarizmi worked during, for ten points, what third Islamic caliphate, the successors of the Umayyads?",
        "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Joyce’s Ulysses, Stephen Daedalus dreams of this aforementioned ruler, the builder of the House of Wisdom.",
        "answer": "Harun al-Rashid"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was first elected as part of the Fifth Republic Movement. This leader called Vincente Fox “the puppy dog of the empire.” During an Ibero-American Summit, King Juan Carlos I asked this leader “Why don’t you shut up?” This leader’s funding led to the establishment of the TeleSUR TV network. He’s not Evo Morales, but this leader promoted “Socialism in the 21st century” as part of his Bolivarian Revolution. For ten points, name this socialist President of Venezuela during most of the 2000s.",
        "answer": "Hugo Chavez"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chavez was succeeded by this man as president of Venezuela. The Popular Will Party staged protests against this leader in 2014.",
        "answer": "Nicolas Maduro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted “your eyes and mine are never destined to see [the] miracle” of “peaceable secession” in a “plea for Harmony and Peace.” That speech, given on the seventh of March, controversially supported the Compromise of 1850, leading to this man’s resignation from the Senate. This man’s reply to Robert Hayne declared “Liberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable!” The 19th century “Great Triumvirate” consisted of John Calhoun, Henry Clay, and, for ten points, what Massachusetts senator?",
        "answer": "Daniel Webster"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daniel Webster was an alumni of this university, whose private charter he defended in the Supreme Court against William Woodward. Webster called this Ivy League school “a small school [...] yet there are those who love it.”",
        "answer": "Dartmouth College"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Twenty-two baboons line the upper frieze of the larger of two structures in this complex, which was rediscovered by Jean-Louis Burckhardt and Giovanni Belzoni. The inner walls of this pair of structures align with the sun in February and October, illuminating statues of Ptah, Ra-Horakhty, Amun, and the pharaoh who constructed these temples. This portion of the Nubian Monuments was moved to protect it from flooding caused by the Aswan High Dam. For ten points, name this pair of Egyptian temples fronted by massive statues of Nefertari and Ramses II.",
        "answer": "Abu Simbel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Temple of Nefertari at Abu Simbel is dedicated to the queen and this cow-headed Egyptian goddess of motherhood.",
        "answer": "Hathor"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "NAFTA",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Economic concept supported by NAFTA, making up the “FT” in the name.",
          "answer": "free trade"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who signed NAFTA into law in 1993.",
          "answer": "Bill Clinton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed agreement between Pacific Rim countries, approved in October 2015, that would supersede some NAFTA agreements.",
          "answer": [
            "Trans-Pacific Partnership",
            "TPP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Third party Presidential candidate who warned that NAFTA would create a “giant sucking sound” of jobs going south.",
          "answer": "H. Ross Perot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican political party whose president, Carlos Salinas, supported NAFTA.",
          "answer": [
            "Institutional Revolutionary Party",
            "Partido Revolucionario Institucional",
            "PRI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican militant group that declared war against Mexico over the feared sale of Native American land under NAFTA.",
          "answer": [
            "Zapatistas or Zapatista Army of National Liberation",
            "Ejercito Zapatista de Leberacion Nacional",
            "EZLN"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican factories that boomed after NAFTA reduced tariffs on importing raw material.",
          "answer": "maquiladoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian Prime Minister who signed NAFTA and rejected the Meech Lake and Charlottetown Accords.",
          "answer": "Brian Mulroney"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Greek Politics",
      "prompt": "In the history of Greek politics, both ancient and modern, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern capital city, which ostracized potential tyrants during its ancient Golden Age.",
          "answer": "Athens"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century BC lawmaker whose remarkably harsh law code inspired a common adjective.",
          "answer": [
            "Draco",
            "draconian and word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for intense spending cuts and tax increases imposed on Greece by the EU in return for a bailout.",
          "answer": [
            "austerity measures",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern right-wing, neo-Nazi party, which holds the third most seats in Greek parliament behind Syriza and New Democracy.",
          "answer": [
            "Golden Dawn or Chrysi Avgi",
            "XA",
            "chi alpha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Syriza and current Prime Minister of Greece.",
          "answer": "Alexis Tsipras"
        },
        {
          "question": "So-called“firstcitizen”ofhiscity-state, whousedtheDelianLeague’streasurytobuildtheParthenon.",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Milesian immigrant and lover of the aforementioned “first citizen,” who may have run a brothel.",
          "answer": "Aspasia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hill just west of the Acropolis, used by Cleisthenes to deliver political reforms to popular assemblies.",
          "answer": "Pnyx"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Saladin",
      "prompt": "In the life and times of Saladin, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country, whose city of Tikrit was the birthplace of both Saladin and Saddam Hussein.",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egypt-based dynasty founded by Saladin after the fall of the Fatimid caliphate.",
          "answer": "Ayyubid dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of Middle Ages religious conflicts, the third of which ended with Saladin’s victory over Christian forces.",
          "answer": [
            "Crusades",
            "Third Crusade"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The holy city defended by Saladin in that conflict.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "The English king who signed the Treaty of Jaffa with Saladin, calling a truce to end that conflict.",
          "answer": "Richard the Lionheart or Richard I"
        },
        {
          "question": "The type of payment collected in England to fund that conflict against Saladin, consisting of a 10% tax collected by bishops.",
          "answer": [
            "tithe",
            "tallage"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "July 1187 battle near a twin-peaked volcano where Saladin captured Guy of Lusignan [loo-sin-yon], triggering the aforementioned conflict.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Horns of Hattin"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in modern northern Israel, captured in that conflict by the freed Guy of Lusignan.",
          "answer": "Acre"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing general of this battle “had not despaired of the Republic” after escaping with seventy horsemen. In the aftermath of this battle, Tarentum and Capua revoked their allegiance with the loser. The winning side placed (20 pts)",
        "Celtic and Spanish forces in the center, where they pulled back, allowing hidden, experienced Libyan soldiers to entrap the losing army in a double-envelopment. Gaius Terentius Varro survived this battle, though (10 pts)",
        "70,000 Romans did not. Victories at Trebia and Lake Trasimene were followed by a massive defeat at, for ten points, what 216 BC battle in southern Italy, a massive tactical victor for Hannibal?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Cannae"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one book by this author, the title peasant is adopted by Frederick Barbarossa and goes in search of the mythical Kingdom of Prester John. In another work of his, the Abbe della Piccola is the alter-ego of Simone Simonini, who is inspired by real-life individuals and forgeries to write The Protocols of the Elders of Zion. This author of (20 pts)",
        "Baudolino and The Prague Cemetery included a fictionalized version of Roger Bacon, (10 pts)",
        "William of Baskerville, in a historical novel about murders in a monastery. For ten points, name this Italian author of The Name of the Rose."
      ],
      "answer": "Umberto Eco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Karl Marx referred to this man as the “most miserable and meanest of blackguards.” While Santiago Marin˜o fought in the east, this man worked with Jos´e F´elix Ribas on the west to defeat an army led by Domingo de Monteverde. This man (20 pts)",
        "wrote about the failures of the First Republic in an 1812 document; nine years later, his forces were victorious at the Battle of Carabobo, allowing this man to (10 pts)",
        "establish, and become the first president of, Gran Colombia. For ten points, name this South American “Liberator,” honored as the namesake of a country with capitals La Paz and Sucre."
      ],
      "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Duchess of Valentinois [val-en-tin-wah] was adopted by a ruler of this country in order to avoid a succession crisis. This country’s highest point is the Chemin de Revoirs [she-min de reh-VWAR], and it built the Fontvielle [font-vee-ell] district by reclaiming (20 pts)",
        "land from the sea. An institution in this country names a set of algorithms for simulating and computing probabilities. This country is currently ruled by the House of (10 pts)",
        "Grimaldi, whose Prince Rainier III married American actress Grace Kelly in 1956. For ten points, name this principality on the French Riviera, known for its casino at Monte Carlo."
      ],
      "answer": "Monaco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler backed the Occasional Conformity Act to bar Catholics from public office. Abigail Masham replaced this ruler’s friendship with Sarah Churchill. William, Duke of Gloucester was the only (20 pts)",
        "child of this ruler to survive past infancy. The Act of Settlement was passed during this ruler’s reign, establishing Electress Sophia as the heiress (10 pts)",
        "presumptive. For ten points, name this British queen, the last monarch of the House of Stuart, during whose reign the Acts of Union united England and Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "Queen Anne"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician said that “Every good Christian ought to kick” Jerry Falwell in support of Sandra Day O’Connor. The “A Time for Choosing” speech supported one campaign of this man, who once called the Eisenhower administration a “dime store New Deal.” This man, who claimed that (20 pts)",
        "“extremism in defense of liberty is no vice,” was the subject of an ad featuring a little girl picking flower petals followed by a (10 pts)",
        "nuclear explosion. The “Daisy” ad targeted, for ten points, what Arizona Republican who lost in a landslide to Lyndon Johnson in 1964?"
      ],
      "answer": "Barry Goldwater"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An abandoned opera by this composer depicted the secret Vehmic courts of medieval Germany, and he wrote another opera based on the memoirs of Florentine sculputor Benvenuto Cellini. This composer of Les francs-juges dedicated a work to veterans of the July (20 pts)",
        "Revolution; four offstage brass bands are called for in that Requiem. He also wrote a five-movement work that includes a “scene in the fields” and combines the Dies Irae [dee-ACE ee-RAY] with its (10 pts)",
        "id´ee fixe [ee-DAY feex] in the final movement, a dream of a witches’ Sabbath. For ten points, what composer’s unrequited love for the singer Harriet Smithson inspired his Symphony Fantastique?"
      ],
      "answer": "Hector Berlioz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing side in this battle gave command to Juan Landero to officially surrender, as Juan Morales refused to do so. During this battle, David Conner’s fleet provided bombardment support on Collado (20 pts)",
        "Beach. After this battle, the winning side marched on the capital, meeting the enemy at Cerro Gordo and capturing Santa Anna’s wooden leg. (10 pts)",
        "Winfield Scott led the first major American amphibious assault in, for ten points, what 1847 three-week siege of a port city on the Gulf of Mexico during the Mexican-American War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle or Siege of Veracruz"
    }
  ]
}